<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Silent Film on the blog of alexandra edwards, phd</title>
        <link>https://nonmodernist.com/blog/tags/silent-film/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Silent Film on the blog of alexandra edwards, phd</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Alexandra Edwards</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2022 00:04:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nonmodernist.com/blog/tags/silent-film/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Just Around the Corner</title>
        <link>https://nonmodernist.com/blog/just-around-the-corner/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2022 00:04:15 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://nonmodernist.com/blog/just-around-the-corner/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://nonmodernist.com/blog/just-around-the-corner/cornerposter.png" alt="Featured image of post Just Around the Corner" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a recently restored film, stitched together from two different prints for two different markets, which I watched through the online version of &lt;em&gt;Le Giornate del cinema muto&lt;/em&gt; (also known as the Pordenone Silent Film Festival).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://nonmodernist.com/blog/blog/just-around-the-corner/cornerlanternslide.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;1381&#34;
	height=&#34;1056&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://nonmodernist.com/blog/blog/just-around-the-corner/cornerlanternslide_hu17244799862558892896.jpg 480w, https://nonmodernist.com/blog/blog/just-around-the-corner/cornerlanternslide_hu16303473966123453646.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;A lantern slide advertising &amp;lsquo;Just Around the Corner&amp;rsquo; (1921)&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;130&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;313px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frances Marion wrote and directed this Fannie Hurst adaptation, after having written the adaptation of Hurst&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Humoresque&lt;/em&gt; the previous year. The film is Hurst through and through—the story of working poor New Yorkers crowded into a tenement, struggling to lead lives that matter, with family tragedy just around the corner&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We meet the Birdsong family: brother and sister Jimmie and Essie, and their mother, who is slowly dying of an incurable heart ailment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hat shop scene early on is a fascinating representation of women&amp;rsquo;s material labor at the time (and maybe a nod to Edith Wharton&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The House of Mirth&lt;/em&gt;?). Hurst and Marion are bold in their pro-labor feminist politics, deftly showing-not-telling that bosses exploit both women&amp;rsquo;s labor and their bodies, and that poor women are forced to accept both the illegal working conditions and the sexual assault because they need money to survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically, when Essie wants to take a job as a theatre usher for better pay, her mother and brother object because of the job&amp;rsquo;s connotations of prostitution. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s night work!&amp;rdquo; Ma Birdsong exclaims. As though Essie wasn&amp;rsquo;t already getting her breasts groped by her aggressive sweatshop boss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film starts to drag a bit as it shifts into full melodrama mode, pairing Essie off with a bad beau who keeps dodging her attempts to bring him home to meet her family. Despite her anti-sex work stance, the sight of Ma Birdsong waiting endlessly at the set dinner table, adjusting the silverware again and again, broke my heart. But the story moves slowly and predictably in this section, really sucking the energy out of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pace picks up somewhat towards the end thanks to the intervention of a big sweet hunk, played by Marion&amp;rsquo;s real-life husband, who arrives just in time to do a whole heap of emotional labor and teach everybody a lesson about non-toxic masculinity. Even in 1921 we loved a &lt;em&gt;deus ex himbo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
